ELISABETH R. PELIKAN, B.Sc. M.Sc.

Curriculum Vitae

HOME Siehdichfürstraße 40

2230 Gänserndorf +43 699 10411342 elisabeth@pelikan-it.com

https://elisabethpelikan.netlify.app/

UNIVERSITY

Universitätsstraße 7 (NIG)

1010 Wien

+43 1 4277 47405

elisabeth.pelikan@univie.ac.at

In my Ph.D. I have researched self-regulation and motivation (based on self-determination theory) in learning contexts during COVID-19. Going forward, I would like to explore how the insights I have gained can be applied in other, more practical contexts such as teacher-student interaction and in sport psychology.

EDUCATION

02/2019 Ph.D. Candidate in Psychologometric Psychologometric Ph.D. Candidate in Psychologometric Psychologom
--

Faculty of Psychology – University of Vienna

10/2016 - 01/2019 M.Sc. in Psychology (passed with distinction)

Faculty of Psychology – University of Vienna

Thesis title: "Language development in very and extremely preterm

infants - A retrospective study"

Thesis supervisor: Ass.-Prof. Mag. Dr. Harald Werneck

10/2014 -07/2016 B.Sc. in Psychology

Faculty of Psychology – University of Vienna

Thesis title: "Nutritional behavior and quality of life in relation to the

residential situation among students" *Thesis supervisor:* Mag. Dr. Laura Brandt

10/2000 - 04/2002 University of Vienna – Faculty of Philosophy and Education –

Pedagogy and philosophy (prematurely terminated)

09/2004 - 06/2006 Educational Institute for Kindergarten Pedagogy (BAKIP) – Certified

kindergarten teacher

ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

10/2020 - ongoing Lecturer – Faculty of Psychology – University of Vienna

02/2019 - ongoing University assistant (prae doc) – Faculty of Psychology – University of

Vienna

09/2017 – 02/2020 Tutor – Faculty of Psychology – University of Vienna

09.2016 - 01.2019 Student Assistant – Faculty of Psychology – University of Vienna

NON-ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

08.2011 - 08.2016	Kindergarten teacher – St. Nikolausstiftung – Vienna
11.2010 - 07.2011	Private daycare – Verein Hotzenplotz – Vienna
03.2010 - 10.2010	Private daycare – Self-employed – Vienna
08.2006 - 10.2010	Kindergarten teacher – Kinder in Wien – Vienna

PARTICIPATION IN FUNDED SCIENTIFIC PROJECTS

2020 - 2022	Scientific project staff in the project "PRO-SRL-TRANSFER - Transfervorhaben zur produkt- und prozessorientierten Modellierung und Erfassung von Kompetenzen zum Selbstregulierten Lernen im Studium" ["PRO-SRL-TRANSFER - Transfer project for product- and process-oriented modeling and recording of competencies for self-regulated learning in studies"] funded by Federal Ministry of Educationand Research Germany
2020 - 2021	Scientific project staff in the project "Lernen unter COVID-19" ["Learning under COVID-19"] at the Faculty of Psychology, University of Vienna – funded by Vienna Science and Technology Fund, the University of Vienna, the City of Vienna and the MEGA Bildungsstiftung
2019 - 2020	Scientific project staff in the project "Aktives Studieren" ["Active Studying"] at the Faculty of Psychology, University of Vienna
2019 - 2022	Scientific project staff in the project "Studierende zum Abschluss motivieren (SAM)" ["Motivate students to graduate"] at the Faculty of Psychology, University of Vienna

AWARDS

06/2022	Teaching Award – University of Vienna
10/2018 - 09/2019	Performance Scholarship – University of Vienna
10/2016 - 09/2017	Performance Scholarship – University of Vienna
10/2014 - 09/2015	Performance Scholarship – University of Vienna

ANCILLIARY ACTIVITIES

05/2021 – ongoing Member of the early career researcher team of the Austrian Network for

Higher Education (Junge Hochschulforschung – JuHoFo)

- Participating in meet-ups
- Co-managing slack space

06/2021 - ongoing Member of the early career researcher team of the Austrian

Psychological Association (Österreichische Gesellschaft für

Psychologie; ÖGP)

- Co-organizing the pre-conference day of the 14th Conference of the Austrian Society of Psychology
- Co-organizing of the COVID-19 fund for early career researchers

CONFERENCE CONTRIBUTIONS & PRESENTATIONS

Oral Presentations & Workshops

- Finsterwald, M. & Pelikan, E. (2022, June 4). How can we best support doctoral candidates? [Workshop] Supervisors' Day 2022 of the Vienna Doctoral School of Social Sciences.
- **Pelikan, E.** (2021, November 3). *Impulsvortrag zum Forum "Neue Lehr- und Lernformen* [Short talk at the forum "New forms of teaching and learning"]. 25. OeaD-Hochschultagung, online.
- **Pelikan, E.**, Holzer, J., Schober, B., Lüftenegger, M. (2021, September, 15). *Welche Rolle spielen Implizite Fähigkeitstheorien für schulisches Wohlbefinden?* [Which role do Implicit ability theories play in school well-being?]. PAEPSY, 2021, online.
- Pelikan, E., Fasching, M., Hager, K., Holzer, J., Korlat, S., Lüftenegger, M., Spiel, C., Schober, B. (2021, June 25). *Lernen unter COVID-19 Bedingungen* [Learning under COVID-19 conditions]. Vernetzungskonferenz des deutschsprachigen Netzwerks für innovative Lernumgebungen, online.
- **Pelikan, E.**, Fasching, M., Hager, K., Holzer, J., Korlat, S., Lüftenegger, M., Reiter, J., Schober, B., Spiel, C. (2021, May 21). *Lernen unter COVID-19 Bedingungen* [Learning under COVID-19 conditions]. Kinderrechte Monitoring Board, Bundeskanzleramt, Sektion Familie und Jugend, online.
- Schober, B., **Pelikan, E.** (2021, April 23). *Selbstreguliertes Lernen und Arbeiten im Studium Voraussetzungen für einen erfolgreichen Abschluss?* [Self-regulated learning and working in studies Prerequisites for successful graduation?] Workshop der Österreichischen Forschungsgemeinschaft: Studierende zum Abschluss motivieren, online.
- Holzer, J., Korlat, S., Lüftenegger, M., **Pelikan, E.**, Spiel, C., Schober, B., & Devaney, C. (2020, October 28 30). *Protective factors for adolescent well-being in times of COVID-19*. 8th International Congress of Educational Sciences and Development, Pontevedra, Spain.
- Korlat, S., Holzer, J., Lüftenegger, M., **Pelikan, E.**, Schober, B., Spiel, C. (2021, April 15). Schooling in COVID-19 – Challenges and Opportunities. PHERECLOS Online Consortium Meeting: Lectures from external experts, online.
- Korlat, S., Holzer, J., Lüftenegger, M., **Pelikan, E.**, Schober, B., Spiel, C. (2021, February 1). *Learning under COVID-19: Challenges for self-regulation.* Word Education Leadership Online Conference, online.
- Spiel, C., **Pelikan, E.** (2020, December 2). *Lernen unter COVID-19 Herausforderungen für die Selbstregulation*. [Learning under COVID-19 Challenges for self-regulation.]Online-Vernetzungskonferenz 2021 Nationale Strategie zur sozialen Dimension in der Hochschulbildung, online.
- Schober, B., **Pelikan, E.** (2020, October 29). *Selbstreguliertes Lernen als Schlüsselkompetenz und Ziel universitärer Lehre*. [Self-regulated learning as a key competence and goal of university teaching.] Teaching Vets-Symposium 6, online.

Poster presentations

Pelikan, E.R., Korlat, S., Holzer, J., Schober, B., Spiel, C., Lüftenegger, M. (2021, December 1). Challenges in Learning under COVID-19 among Adolescents: Gender and Age Differences. digiGEBF2021, online. https://www.doi.org/10.13140/RG.2.2.17362.89280

MEDIA

- Interview at the Ars Boni Podcast (24.06.21) https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yDquGceUaeE
- Contribution for the Vienna Children's University (co-author) https://kinderuni.online/kurs/tipps-und-tricks-fuer-den-schulalltag/

REVIEWING

- Computers & Education
- European Journal of Developmental Psychology
- Psychology Research and Behavior Management
- Zeitschrift für Evaluation der DeGEval
- Leykam Verlag

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

03/2021 – 06/2022	Übung: "Präsentations- und Moderationstechniken" [Exercise: "Presentation- and Moderationtechniques"] – University of Vienna
10/2021 - 01/2022	Anwendungsseminar: "Wissenschaftskommunikation: Wissenschaftliche Befunde und Fachwissen erfolgreich vermitteln - von Schule bis Parlament" [Application Seminar: "Science Communication: Successfully Communicating Scientific Findings and Expertise - from School to Parliament"] – University of Vienna
10/2021 - 01/2022	Übung: "Präsentations- und Moderationstechniken" [Exercise: "Presentation- and Moderationtechniques"] – University of Vienna
03/2021 – 06/2021	Übung: "Präsentations- und Moderationstechniken" [Exercise: "Presentation- and Moderationtechniques"] – University of Vienna
10/2020 - 01/2021	Übung: "Präsentations- und Moderationstechniken" [Exercise: "Presentation- and Moderationtechniques"] – University of Vienna

COURSES AND FURTHER EDUCATION

12/2021	Data manipulation with dplyr – Datacamp (Data Scientist Career Track)
12/2021	Introduction to the Tidyverse – Datacamp (Data Scientist Career Track)
12/2021	Intermediate R – Datacamp (Data Scientist Career Track)
12/2021	Introduction to R – Datacamp (Data Scientist Career Track)
09/2021	Negotiation and conflict – University of Vienna
06/2021	Conversation in English: Conference & Meeting Situations – University of Vienna
06/2021	COIL (Collaborative Online International Learning) – University of Vienna
05/2021	Present better - Appear confident in online meetings – University of Vienna
04/2021	Publication Strategies in the Academic "Publish or Perish" Competition – University of Vienna
WS 2020/21	Latent Variable Modeling in Mplus – University of Vienna
09/2020	E-Moderation: Design and communicate online tasks – University of Vienna
SS 2020	Scientific Writing – University of Vienna
WS 2019/21	Doing Open Science – University of Vienna
WS 2019/21	Multilevel Modeling for Experimental and Longitudinal Data in R – University of Vienna

06/2019	"R" for advanced users – University of Vienna
04/2019	Introduction to "R" – University of Vienna
04/2019	The Master Seminar: Supervising during the Semester
03/2019	Basic Qualification for Junior Staff - Teaching in Higher Education – University of Vienna
04/2017	Getting and Cleaning Data – Coursera (Johns Hopkins University)
11/2016	R Programming – Coursera (Johns Hopkins University)
10/2016	The Data Scientist's Toolbox – Coursera (Johns Hopkins University)

LIST OF PUBLICATIONS

First author publications

- Pelikan, E. R., Lüftenegger, M., Fasching, M., Fassl, F., Hager, K., Holzer, J., Korlat, S., Mayerhofer, M., Reiter, J., Schober, B., & Spiel, C. (2022). *Lernen während der Pandemie Erfahrungen und Implikationen aus der COVID-19 Krise*. [Manuscript in preperation]
- Pelikan, E. R., Grützmacher, L., Hager, K., Holzer, J., Korlat, S., Mayerhofer, M., Schober, B., Spiel, C., & Lüftenegger, M. (2022). *The role of basic need statisfaction for intrinsic motivation and self-regulated learning during COVID-19: A longitudinal study*. [Manuscript in preperation]
- Pelikan, E. R., Finsterwald, M., Dresel, M., Rinas, R., Schober, B., Lüftenegger, M., (2022). Selbstreguliertes Lernen und Metakognition in der Erwachsenenebildung. Theoretische Grundlagen und praktische Anwendung. [Manuscript submitted].
- Pelikan, E., Rinas, R., Finsterwald, M., Dresel, M., Eckerlein, N., Schober, B. & Lüftenegger, M. (2022). Selbstreguliertes Lernen im Studium: Bedarfsgerechte Unterstützung von Studierenden. Ein Kompendium für Lehrende und Studiengangsverantwortliche. https://doi.org/10.25365/phaidra.332
- Pelikan, E., Reiter, J., Bergen, K., Lüftenegger, M., Holzer, J., Korlat, S., Schober, B., & Spiel, C. (2022). Lernen unter COVID-19 Bedingungen: Zur Situation der Studierenden in Österreich. In H. Angenent, J. Petri, & T. Zimenkova (Eds.), *Bildungsforschung: Hochschulen in der Pandemie* (1st ed., Vol. 9, pp. 200–215). transcript Verlag. https://doi.org/10.14361/9783839459843-013
- Pelikan, E. R., Korlat, S., Reiter, J., Holzer, J., Mayerhofer, M., Schober, B., Spiel, C., Hamzallari, O., Uka, A., Chen, J., Välimäki, M., Puharić, Z., Anusionwu, K. E., Okocha, A. N., Zabrodskaja, A., Salmela-Aro, K., Käser, U., Schultze-Krumbholz, A., Wachs, S., ... Lüftenegger, M. (2021). Distance learning in higher education during COVID-19: The role of basic psychological needs and intrinsic motivation for persistence and procrastination—a multi-country study. *PLOS ONE, 16*(10), e0257346. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0257346
- Pelikan, E., Hager, K., Holzer, J., Korlat, S., Spiel, C., Schober, B., & Lüftenegger, M. (2021). Emergency Distance Learning in Austria during COVID-19: Selected Findings and Implications. *Digital Psychology*, 2(2), 19–22. https://doi.org/10.24989/dp.v2i2.2018
- Pelikan, E. R., Lüftenegger, M., Holzer, J., Korlat, S., Spiel, C., & Schober, B. (2021). Learning during COVID-19: The role of self-regulated learning, motivation, and procrastination for perceived competence. *Zeitschrift Für Erziehungswissenschaft, 24*(2), 393–418. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11618-021-01002-x

Co-author publications

Holzer, J., Korlat, S., **Pelikan, E.**, Schober, B., Spiel, C., & Lüftenegger, M., (2022). *The role of parental self-efficacy regarding parental support for adolescents' coping, self-regulated learning, learning self-efficacy and positive emotions.* [Manuscript in preparation].

- Holzer, J., Korlat, S., Haider, C., Mayerhofer, M., **Pelikan, E.**, Schober, B., Spiel, C., Toumazi, T., Salmela-Aro, K., Käser, U., Schultze-Krumbholz, A., Wachs, S., Dabas, M., Verma, S., Iliev, D., Andonovska-Trajkovska, D., Plichta, P., Pyżalski, J., Walter, N., ... Lüftenegger, M. (2021). Adolescent well-being and learning in times of COVID-19 A multi-country study of basic psychological need satisfaction, learning behavior, and the mediating roles of positive emotion and intrinsic motivation. *PLOS ONE*, *16*(5), e0251352. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0251352
- Holzer, J., Lüftenegger, M., Käser, U., Korlat, S., **Pelikan, E.**, Schultze-Krumbholz, A., Spiel, C., Wachs, S., & Schober, B. (2021). Students' basic needs and well-being during the COVID-19 pandemic: A two-country study of basic psychological need satisfaction, intrinsic learning motivation, positive emotion and the moderating role of self-regulated learning. *International Journal of Psychology*, ijop.12763. https://doi.org/10.1002/ijop.12763
- Holzer, J., Lüftenegger, M., Korlat, S., **Pelikan, E.**, Salmela-Aro, K., Spiel, C., & Schober, B. (2021). Higher Education in Times of COVID-19: University Students' Basic Need Satisfaction, Self-Regulated Learning, and Well-Being. *AERA Open, 7*, 233285842110031. https://doi.org/10.1177/23328584211003164
- Kollmayer, M., Korlat, S., Holzer, J., Lüftenegger, M., **Pelikan, E. R.**, Spiel, C., & Schober, B. (2022). *Digital learning during COVID-19: An intersectional perspective on secondary students' motivation and perceived teacher support*. [Manuscript submitted].
- Korlat, S., Reiter, J., Yanagida, T., Holzer, J., **Pelikan, E.**, Schober, B., Spiel, C., Lüftenegger, M. (2022). Congruent or Conflicted During the COVID-19 Pandemic: The Role of Social Norms and Norm Conflict in Adolescents' Rule Adherence and Well-being. [Manuscript submitted].
- Korlat, S., Reiter, J., Kollmayer, M., Holzer, J., **Pelikan, E.**, Schober, B., Spiel, C., & Lüftenegger, M. (2022). Basic psychological needs and agency and communion during the COVID-19 pandemic: Gender differentials and the role of well-being in adolescence and early adulthood. *Journal of Individual Differences*. [Manuscript accepted for publication].
- Korlat, S., Holzer, J., Reiter, J., Pelikan, E. R., Schober, B., Spiel, C., & Lüftenegger, M. (2022). *The role of the Big Two in socially responsible behavior during the COVID-19 pandemic: Agency and communion in adolescents' personal norm and behavioral adherence to instituted measures.* PLOS ONE, 17(6), e0269018. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0269018
- Korlat, S., Kollmayer, M., Holzer, J., Lüftenegger, M., **Pelikan, E. R.**, Schober, B., & Spiel, C. (2021). Gender Differences in Digital Learning During COVID-19: Competence Beliefs, Intrinsic Value, Learning Engagement, and Perceived Teacher Support. *Frontiers in Psychology, 12*, 637776. https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2021.637776